<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-05-31T16:53:27-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Machine Learning | Topological Defects</title><subtitle>We are a group of graduate and undergradate students at University of Colorado Boulder, investigating the application of machine learning to the physics of 2D liquid crystal films</subtitle><author><name>Adam Green</name></author><entry><title type="html">Welcome</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/05/31/welcome.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome" /><published>2019-05-31T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-05-31T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/05/31/welcome</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/05/31/welcome.html">&lt;p&gt;We are a group of graduate and undergraduate students at the University of Colorado Boulder, investigating the use of machine learning in experimental physics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow our journey in real time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what&quot;&gt;what?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of his thesis, Adam Green was studying the interaction of topological defects in 2D systems. In the lab, we can create quasi-2D fluids by drawing a liquid crystal film over an aperature. We then inject energy into the system (read: hit it really hard), which creates little ‘kinks’ in the fluid, which we can study using polarized-light microscopy. To put it shortly, the interaction of these kinks is interesting to some people (read: physicists).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-machine-learning-though&quot;&gt;why machine learning though&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what our experimental data looks like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous efforts have required the hand-tagging of each defect. Once that is done, statistics can be run on the collection. However, because this is such an arduous process, it severly limits how much data can be analyzed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I didn’t want to spend months squinting over a screen, clicking at pixels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, this seemed like a natural job for machine learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-wait&quot;&gt;but wait…&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are familiar with machine learning, you know that you have to feed your little robot with training data– ie. data that is tagged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So have we really won here? We still have to go into experimental data and hand tag it to generate training data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well…yes and no. Of course, at the end of the day, we do need some hand-tagged experimental images to verify that our process is giving good results, but because the physical system is fairly simple, we may be able to simulate ‘fake’ experiments on the computer and generate training data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2D tilted liquid crystal films can be described by the 2D XY model&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, which has a rich history in physics. We will discuss the 2D XY model in a future post, but for now just know that there are methods to numerically solve the 2D XY model. We can use these methods to generate ‘fake’ experiments, which we can then use as training data. At least, that’s the hope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--- If you like TeXt, don't forget to give me a star. :star2:

 [![Star This Project](https://img.shields.io/github/stars/kitian616/jekyll-TeXt-theme.svg?label=Stars&amp;style=social)](https://github.com/kitian616/jekyll-TeXt-theme/)
 ---&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Not that well though, as the XY model completely neglects hydrodynamics and the liquid-crystal film is, well, liquidy. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>adam</name></author><category term="xymodel," /><category term="ml" /><summary type="html">We are a group of graduate and undergraduate students at the University of Colorado Boulder, investigating the use of machine learning in experimental physics. Follow our journey in real time! what? As part of his thesis, Adam Green was studying the interaction of topological defects in 2D systems. In the lab, we can create quasi-2D fluids by drawing a liquid crystal film over an aperature. We then inject energy into the system (read: hit it really hard), which creates little ‘kinks’ in the fluid, which we can study using polarized-light microscopy. To put it shortly, the interaction of these kinks is interesting to some people (read: physicists). why machine learning though This is what our experimental data looks like. Previous efforts have required the hand-tagging of each defect. Once that is done, statistics can be run on the collection. However, because this is such an arduous process, it severly limits how much data can be analyzed. Also, I didn’t want to spend months squinting over a screen, clicking at pixels. So, this seemed like a natural job for machine learning. but wait… If you are familiar with machine learning, you know that you have to feed your little robot with training data– ie. data that is tagged. So have we really won here? We still have to go into experimental data and hand tag it to generate training data. Well…yes and no. Of course, at the end of the day, we do need some hand-tagged experimental images to verify that our process is giving good results, but because the physical system is fairly simple, we may be able to simulate ‘fake’ experiments on the computer and generate training data. 2D tilted liquid crystal films can be described by the 2D XY model1, which has a rich history in physics. We will discuss the 2D XY model in a future post, but for now just know that there are methods to numerically solve the 2D XY model. We can use these methods to generate ‘fake’ experiments, which we can then use as training data. At least, that’s the hope. Not that well though, as the XY model completely neglects hydrodynamics and the liquid-crystal film is, well, liquidy. &amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Post with Header Image</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/06/01/header-image.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Post with Header Image" /><published>2018-06-01T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-06-01T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/06/01/header-image</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/06/01/header-image.html">&lt;p&gt;A Post with Header Image, See &lt;a href=&quot;https://tianqi.name/jekyll-TeXt-theme/samples.html#page-layout&quot;&gt;Page layout&lt;/a&gt; for more examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;</content><author><name>Adam Green</name></author><category term="TeXt" /><summary type="html">A Post with Header Image, See Page layout for more examples.</summary></entry></feed>